[Music]
good evening good day hello everybody
welcome to the latest live episode i
think it's number 82
of the ask a budget show and as you know
today is a live video chat show which
means i am going to be taking your
questions on video chat face to face
uh so i'm going to share the link for
joining
now
let me
share that
right away and please uh make sure that
you have a reasonably good stable
internet connection because we will need
to hear you and see you so i am sharing
the link now let me pin it so that
everybody gets to see that
okay now the link and the message is
pinned hopefully yeah there you go
so you should be able to uh click on the
link tap on the link through your device
laptop phone whatever it is and join the
video chat
and
the rule is very simple one question per
person so that everybody gets the chance
i want to give as many people as
possible the chance to uh interact ask
questions etc
so
uh let's i look forward to
some of you join i can see people
joining wonderful that's
great uh yes i can see so i think 10
people can join at a time so some of you
may have to wait so
there you go and i can see people have
already joined
okay so whom shall we bring in i'm gonna
bring in people at random
okay
let's begin with
whom shall we begin with
let us begin with
very nice to meet you sir very nice to
meet you what's your question
[Music]
okay so i'm gonna take the question
about the military coup because it's one
question for per person so
india is the kind of country where a
military coup
is not possible it's too large a country
it's too diverse a country so there is
this very interesting book called kudeta
by edward luther let me try and share
that on the screen so that people can
see that
[Music]
just a
minute
let me share that so people can see that
book and the book talks about the
the mechanics etc of a coup
one second a minute
screen
so this book it's available on various
online platforms it's called kudita a
practical handbook revised edition by
edward luthor it's a very old book
actually it's uh this is this seems to
be a newer edition
but it was written in the 20th century
so that's what the book is about it's
about how it's a practical handbook
uh one second where are you
yeah it's a practical handbook on how to
conduct how to uh manufacture how to
plan et cetera and execute a coup d'etat
so it says that there are a number of
conditions that need to be prevalent in
a country for a coup d'etat
and one of the conditions is that there
needs to be i don't remember exactly
what it is there needs to be autocracy
there needs to be a
large population that is disaffected and
there needs to be homogeneity and
uniformity of the population so in india
the population is so diverse and there
are so many different centers of power
in india because of the federal
structure and so on that it is simply
impossible to carry out a coup you may
carry out a coup in delhi but the rest
of the country will just ignore it or
oppose that and they will not be able to
succeed
that is the primary reason
why a coup d'etat is simply not possible
in a country
like india
all right sir thank you very much for
your question
okay let's bring in somebody else uh who
else do we have who else do we have
let's bring in
good evening sir
hi how are you doing
i cannot hear you
can you speak please
hello yes now you're audible because you
spoke
okay yes sir what's your question
my question we know that according to
observer observer effect that
particles are in the form of
waves but but waves but we win but when
we see them their wave perhaps they
become collapsed
and they become particles
do you think that
they also have consciousness like us
okay it's about consciousness and
particle so there is one there are these
philosophical theories there are let me
let me tell you about two philosophical
theories one is called pan psychism the
other one is called cosmopsychism so
according to these theories which belong
in the realm of philosophy consciousness
is something
that permeates the universe
every
every rock every plant every
particle has some element of
consciousness in it so that is the
theory of pan psychism there is
consciousness everywhere but the level
of consciousness is different so uh
from what we know human beings seem to
have the highest consciousness we need
to be we seem to be the most conscious
of all species
animals may have us maybe a lower
consciousness are they self-aware or not
there are these various questions being
raised by scientists etc so we're not
quite sure but obviously if you interact
with animals it's clear that they have a
consciousness they are aware of
themselves they are aware of us they
seem to have emotions at least the
animals that we interact with dogs cats
horses cattle etc
and so on
so consciousness seems to be present in
living beings
are microbes microorganisms conscious
they certainly seem to be aware of the
need for self-preservation and all that
in some way so is there a limited form
of consciousness consciousness there
and is consciousness also
present in non-living objects so these
are the questions that are kind of
the the matter of debate
in philosophy in the realm of science we
still don't even have a definition of
what consciousness is
so in science we don't talk about
consciousness because we don't have a
definition there is some talk in quantum
physics or observing effect etc there is
this theory called the
this interpretation of quantum mechanics
called the uh
for neumann wigner interpretation i
think it is one of these interpretations
in which they say consciousness is is
central to the operable effect there are
other interpretations that do not agree
so it's it's all up in the air right now
and then like i said there is this
theory of cosmos psychism which says
that the entire universe is a conscious
entity there's a universal consciousness
and we are part of that so these are
theories that are around but in science
in when we talk talking strictly about
science we don't have answers yet so
that's the kind of overall overview i
can offer to you sir
all right
thank you
thank you very much for your question
nice to meet you too nice to meet you
bye
okay
let's bring in some other friends of
ours let's bring in mr
rohin
good evening sir
how are you sir
i'm good i'm good nice to meet you to be
honest
nice to meet you sir
so i've been watching your show from
last lot of time so i've been following
you from last one year onwards thank you
thank you thank you so much
so my question is i have seen your lotto
pod podcast and i again and against uh
heard of a lot of patterns in the
history which you keep talking about and
also i've heard about the the genocides
which were convicted and which were
being hidden so now my just one question
is there considering the current
constitution which we have is it
possible to reverse these things or is
it possible to reverse the demographic
changes which have already happened over
the past for example 500 years or after
the independence does our current
constitution allow for that and what is
the future for us means in this coming
hundred years is it possible to happen
see demographic changes that you are
mentioning that of course did happen our
society was forcibly re-engineered you
know social engineering demographic
re-engineering that happened during the
uh
past 1000 years of foreign occupation of
india so what you are saying is true now
the constitution of india is a foreign
constitution it it imposes all kinds of
limitations on our behavior and what
sort of culture we can adopt what we
cannot do and all that and clearly it's
hindu phobic and all that now the
question is about re-engineering the
demographics see yes
re-engineering demographics
is something that would uh
if you if somebody would attempt to do
such a thing it would take a long time i
mean our demographics were re-engineered
over the past 1000 years we're not going
to re-engineer them in the next 20 years
or even 100 years it takes time so this
is a project that we
see
first of all the thing is that everybody
has i i truly believe that everybody has
the right to practice whatever culture
religion they want now the thing is
today we are seeing attempts to still
re-engineer our society by having these
forcible conversions induced conversions
with money and all that so firstly that
needs to stop everybody has the right to
practice their religion whatever
religion they want leave any religion
they want but they should be voluntary
it should not be induced by outside
forces so that is one thing that needs
to be taken care of and i think india is
a large very large civilization the
oldest civilization if you leave india
alone for the next 200 years it will
reconfigure itself naturally
so what needs to happen is that these
forces which are acting from outside
and trying they are trying to actively
re-engineer our society right now that
is what needs to stop if we stop that
and if we stop all the propaganda then
in the next 200 300 years india will
find an equilibrium of its own india is
a very large very ancient very mature
civilization we don't need to
as long as the outside forces are gone
everything will reconfigure itself
naturally organically over time so
that's what needs to happen the
constitution is extraordinarily harmful
to our country
to our culture if you look at the the
constitution of sri lanka for instance
they it is recognized that buddhism is
the paramount culture in sri lanka
because it is the native culture there
for instance i mean there are many other
examples that one can give in india it
is explicitly stated that we have to be
secular and we have to essentially there
are clauses of the constitution that are
explicitly hindu phobic in nature and
the policies of the government are
deeply hindu phobic our temples are
controlled and they all the wealth is
stolen from and other
communities etc they are allowed to
do whatever they want in their places of
worship without interference so there is
selective interference in our places of
worship so these problems exist
and and you know what it all tells you
it tells you that india is not a free
country even today we have been
independent supposedly for 75 years but
that independence is the same as
india has been independent for 75 years
the same way that manmohan singh was
prime minister for 10 years only in name
so these things need to happen there are
foreign forces very powerful forces that
are still acting here we don't see them
we don't realize it so india needs to
become more powerful economically
militarily maybe in the next 10 20 years
then we can start taking
control back from the outside forces so
excellent questions and i hope i
answered it
yeah sure thank you so much thank you
thank you so much nice meeting you thank
you bye-bye
all right i can see um who else who else
do i see
let us bring in
naman
good evening good evening
good evening sir
thank you
nice to meet you nice to meet you sir
yes sir i've been following you since
your video of changes khan showed up and
i was very shocked to see your point of
view and
thank you thank you so what my question
is that india
the indian subcontinent has fragmented
into many parts
and after independence in 1971
when indian army helped
bangladesh to get freedom from pakistan
so why didn't
it became to
get separate country and why did we
include bangladesh in our country is
there any diplomatic reason
and
yeah so
yeah so what you are stating is
absolutely correct
in 1971 when we freed the people of
bengal of of
east bengal bangladesh from pakistani
occupation and operation
that part of the subcontinent had been
separated from india for like 23 or so
years only just a couple of decades
so
i still don't have answers myself as to
why we did not reintegrate bangladesh
with india because as a as it is today
there are millions tens of millions of
bangladeshis running around our country
illegal immigrants and they have now all
the documentation and everything so they
they essentially are here to stay and
this is a means of re-engineering the
internal demographics of india so
yeah bangladesh
yeah so so india should have
reintegrated bangladesh that the
question is why did we not do it so that
is something the congress leadership of
that time can answer unfortunately they
are no longer around one can only
speculate as to why it was not done
uh maybe there was foreign interference
india was a weak country at the time
they were able to beat pakistan but we
were not nothing compared to the two
superpowers of the time the ussr in the
us and they also want see the thing is
that
so many wars have happened in the 20th
century
around the world lots of conflicts are
happening even today and
to tell you the truth many of these or
most of these conflicts are engineered
by various big powers in order to keep
the world churning and in order to
maintain the relevance
in the world so uh
if india had reintegrated bangladesh
it's india's
territorial uh
extent would have grown india's power
would have grown and i suspect that the
superpowers did not want india to become
too big and too powerful so maybe they
armed twisted india and coerced india
into not reintegrating bangladesh and
keeping it allowing it to become an
independent country we don't have any
evidence that corroborates this i can
only speculate but yeah this is
something that
that needs to be looked at and maybe the
leadership of that time if somebody from
that time is around they should answer
it so good question sir
thank you sir thank you
thank you thank you nice meeting you bye
all right let's bring in mr
[Music]
good evening sir hello
good evening sir good evening good
evening nice to meet you hello nice to
meet you
uh sir my question is uh we uh i have
been following your podcast and hearing
the about forced conversion so sir why
these abrahamic religions are so
determined for
converting these polytheistic cultures
it is written in their holy texts it is
the means by which they have always
expanded if you look at the history of
europe in the past 2000 years
i think christianity is something that
emerged in the middle east the christian
cult it was a small
small fringe cult at the time and there
was a it is alleged that there was a
great deal of operation of christianity
then christianity spread across europe
and it became the official state
religion of the roman empire byzantine
empire under constantine the great
and then there was this policy of
spreading it by force so you can see
that
the historians talk about the crusades
but they don't talk about the northern
crusades that happened in europe in
which there was there were large-scale
massacres forced convergence induced
conversions so if you look at the
history of christianity and let me let
me give you a give a very good reference
for that just give me a second let me
share my screen um
all right just a second so i will give a
book reference
let me
share the screen
what on earth is that
okay let me do it again i think it's not
been shared properly just give me a
second
so if you look at this
book it is by uh an author called
catherine nixie the darkening age the
christian destruction of the classical
world it demonstrates it details
uh it goes into great detail about how
christianity as a religion as a
as a political uh
force
systematically destroyed the culture of
rome of greece the various indigenous
indo-european cultures that are very
similar to
our vedic culture and so on so it goes
into great detail in how this happened
so it is part of the uh of the framework
of the abrahamic religions that you have
to expand by force it's it's typically
been by force and this is inherent to i
would say almost every abrahamic
religion i think judaism doesn't do it
judaism has a different sort of
practice it is more organic more
localized but the other ones are this
way so that is the reason why it is
inherent in the structure of the
abrahamic religions that they spread
they are expansionist their exclusivist
and they spread by force this is very
well known scholars have written tons
and tons of articles and books about
this there is nothing controversial
about this so that's the reason why it
is so
all right sir
thank you sir thank you thank you sir
thank you nice to meet you thank you bye
all right let us bring in somebody else
let us bring in
rakshith
hi
hi sir thank you for the sun how are you
doing
it was good uh how wonderful
wonderful wonderful very nice
first thing to your viewers sir don't
interrupt when sir is talking it's you
know he is not able to answer and you
are you are in the confusion altogether
so let's let him speak first so my
question is sir as we know in this know
the situation of ukraine what's
happening there
and uh us will intervene if russia
intervenes ukraine u.s have to intervene
because west is not that powerful the
western countries are not that powerful
that powerful that they will be they
will be able to stop russia so if u.s in
intervenes in the ukraine china will you
know uh
intervene uh
taiwan and once they do that
the next threat is us arunachal pradesh
in every every you know far eastern part
of india that will be the next thread so
what should india do in that particular
matter what should we do
like should we intervene
in china
so you raise a very interesting and
important point so in india we talk
about a two-front war with china on one
side and pakistan on the other side the
west is facing a similar situation there
is this big
russian pressure being applied in
eastern europe in ukraine and
simultaneously we have the chinese
pressure in the streets of taiwan they
are always threatening to invade taiwan
and like you said that if the russians
make a move here the chinese will most
likely make a simultaneous move in
taiwan and then the us will be faced
with a dilemma
of what do we do because if the u.s
allows such a thing to happen they will
immediately lose their superpower status
whatever cloud they had and people will
stop respecting them and fearing them so
this is
a big problem for the us now analysts
would say that this is
not going to happen immediately
there is this winter olympics that's
going to happen in china the west is
boycotting it diplomatically they're not
sending the representatives and so on
so the chinese are facing pressure
because of their actions in essentially
in the uh
in xinjiang whatever they're doing to
the igor people nothing for tibet
tibetans don't matter so the chinese are
facing pressure because of their actions
in xinjiang
and they want this event to go off
smoothly and that's why the russians are
right now
coordinating with the chinese and
putting pressure on ukraine so that the
west's attention is over there
but like you said in the eventuality
that there is an invasion either of
ukraine or or taiwan
then india will be in a dilemma because
if the chinese take over let's forget
about ukraine it's not important from
our perspective
but if the chinese take over taiwan it's
then they're going to be free to take
over the indian ocean if they succeed in
that
so what should india do now india should
do whatever it can based on its current
capabilities india is still not
the match of china in the indian ocean
in from the naval perspective or from
certain other perspectives but india has
a great uh
very good position when it comes to the
himalayas and the near abroad in the
indian ocean
so
if the political leadership is so
willing then in case there is a chinese
invasion of taiwan india should
immediately
secure nepal
and sri lanka that's what india should
do
so because nepal and sri lanka have been
under chinese influence for quite some
time the chinese have been interfering
in the indian ocean they are creating
this uh
what do they call it the string of
pearls to encircle india and in the
himalayas and beyond that also they're
trying to encircle india as well so if
the chinese do such a thing india should
immediately secure nepal and sri lanka
if the political leadership is so
willing and i think it should not be
difficult to do that we have the
capability and the wherewithal to do
that so that's what i would say should
happen but it all depends on the
willingness of the political leadership
of india yes sir
uh as you said that you know let's say
china intervenes the taiwan okay
pakistan is not in a condition that they
can attack us they're not financially
stable right now so we can attack china
and it will be a two front wall for
china and they are not in china is a
superpower in terms of economy but they
are not a superpower in terms of
military can we do that
it all depends on how much the other
forces other powers will cooperate with
india how much support do we get from
the u.s essentially especially in the
indian ocean-indo-pacific region if they
assist us then we can do these things
pakistan is not really a big problem
they will look out for themselves the
chinese may do something so it's a
complicated issue but if india gets the
support
it's at least in the indian ocean region
in the pacific region then we can do
these things so it will depend on those
factors as well
okay so just last thing i wanted to have
a i have a small query does language
help only one question per person sir
only one question per person just a
simple question i have to be fair to
everybody everybody gets one question
sir okay thank you all right
thank you so much for coming good great
question thank you bye
okay
let's bring in mr pranav
well hello
hello sir
how are you doing
sorry i'm fine sir
have you been on this show before
yeah yes sir i've been on the phone
nice to meet you again yes sir so sir my
question is that you have released your
video on your interaction with dr neeraj
rai
it was a very interesting one
so sir can you summarize the entire
video and tell the output of that video
okay let me summarize the the video
essentially what dr nirajaray has
demonstrated through
the interaction that i had with him and
also through his papers all his research
is that the aryan dravidian divide is a
myth
there is no such thing as a aryan race
and a dravidian race it is a lie we are
from the genetic perspective the same
people throughout the indian
subcontinent yes there are all kinds of
different uh genetic inputs small minor
inputs here and there the northeast has
the the dimension of of genetic inputs
from the eastern part of asia and so on
but overall the indian subcontinent is
one genetic population and the the
entire aryan dravidian thing is a myth
the ancestral north indian ancestral
south indian categorization that has
been created is also completely baseless
it is a lie it has been uh created by
cherry picking data and only taking data
that is convenient so that essentially
was the gist of the conversation there
are many other points that were
discussed i mean uh he also mentioned
that india is the true cradle of
civilization from the perspective of
agriculture the presence of agriculture
is attested from the archaeological
record in india to be the oldest in the
known world more than ten thousand years
ago we had rice cultivation and so many
other things so we discussed a whole lot
of things but the main
takeaway i would say is the complete
destruction the complete total demise of
the aryan invasion or migration theory
and the myth of a separate aryan race
and dravidian race so that's how i can
summarize it for you sir
thank you sir sir one small suggestion
uh can you call this
author vikram sampath he has done a lot
of research work on veer sawarkar so it
will be very interesting for him to be
in this podcast show of yours vikram
sampath
thank you for the suggestion appreciate
it thank you
bye
okay who else
is in
here
let us bring in mr
who else do we have i can see two people
here dilip reddy
well hello
hello
how are you doing yes yes sir
sir i want to know
who is the most powerful in india which
can who can control
and change the constitution
okay okay so who is powerful enough in
india today to
who would be powerful enough to change
the constitution as of today nobody
nobody is is powerful enough to change
the constitution the consideration is
deeply entrenched in the system recently
i mean not recently a few years ago the
the current government tried to amend
the constitution and create this what
was the amendment it was the njac
judicial amendment to make the judiciary
more accountable and the indian supreme
court immediately threw it out even
though it was constitutionally done
properly
the the entire um all the states were
taken into the picture into
consideration and it was done as per the
correct process
this constitutional amendment and yet
the supreme court simply threw it out it
kind of tells you that the supreme court
in some way even though it's an
unelected unaccountable body in india
which
is unaccountable and unelected and still
they seem to be in some ways more
powerful than the elected government of
india they can just throw out an
amendment because they don't like it and
they made some excuses it goes against
the so-called
fundament fundamental structure or code
structure of the constitution or
something which the which is the term
they have invented recently looks like
so they want to keep appointing judges
themselves themselves and that sort of
thing so as of today as is demonstrated
by this incident even the prime minister
of india and the entire elected
system of it electoral system of india
is not powerful enough to even make a
small amendment that the judiciary
doesn't like
so as of today it is not possible for
anybody in india
to
change the constitution we are talking
about something bigger we are talking
about the fact that we need to get rid
of this foreign constitution and
create a new one that is indian in
nature and as of today it is just a pipe
dream it may be remain a pipe dream for
the next 10 20 years also so that is the
situation we are living in we are not
really free
you see so
that's what i can tell you sir gentlemen
thank you for the question
all right thank you for the question bye
bye
nice to meet you all
okay let us bring in somebody else
uh um us bring in um
mr
rishab singh
hello good evening
can't hear you sir can't hear you you're
muted
thank you so much thank you
so my question is
do the genetics disappear
for example throughout our history we
see when a invading force invades a
country so does the genetic nature of
that particular area of territory
changes for example if you take the case
of turkey
when the turks colonize turkey does the
does did they
change the entire genetic makeup of that
territory because some people today
claim that the modern turks are not the
designers of
uh the greeks that lived in the
pre-turkic area
the invading turkic people so what is
your view on this
yeah that's a very good question so
let's take the example of turkey so what
we know from history
is that the present bay country of
turkey let's go to the map and let me
show the map so that it's clear to
everyone
uh just give me a second i will share
the map on the screen
if it will
open okay where is the map
here's the map of the world go to turkey
so we know where india is let's go
westwards towards turkey so this here is
turkey this is the modern nation of
turkey
the peninsula region is called anatolia
historically it has been called anatolia
so the turkic peoples
they originated in
eastern asia
okay in north in the northern part of
eastern asia north of mongolia and
siberia etcetera
that's the homeland original homeland of
the turkic people
now because of the sudden expansion of
the mongol empire in the 13th century
the turks fled from that and they went
westwards
into present day kazakhstan present-day
eastern europe and then they went
southwards and then that's how they
entered the present-day geographical
region of turkey anatolia now anatolia
was not empty at the time it was home to
an indigenous population the ori
essentially is old greece
if you look at the archaeological
remains etc you find uh in turkey in
present day turkey you will find
elements of greek architecture roman
architecture all that so it was home to
an indigenous greek population now what
happened is that these
conquering turks they were very small in
number compared to the original
population of greece what they did was
they did genocide massacres all that and
then they
uh took the women captive and had
children with them so if you look at the
original turkic people they look very
different from today's
citizens of turkey today's citizens
correct correct you're right
and today's citizens of turkey they look
like europeans they look like the local
greeks armenians georgians etc so they
if you examine their genetics you may
find
turkic patrilineal lineages in them but
the matrilineal lineages and overall
genetics are local european anatolian
greek
georgian are
armenian bulgarian etc slavic perhaps to
some extent mostly greek and uh and
caucasus region or genetics so that's
what happened so when a conquering
population comes into a region like this
uh the genetic input is is very little
for instance the turks conquered india
as well they were
ruling india for quite some time
northern india mostly eventually other
parts of india but if you look at the
genetics of the indian muslims you will
find almost no turkic or foreign
contribution in that and that has been
demonstrated multiple times through
genetic research and people talk about
aryan invasion etc where is the genetics
for that we have all the same genetics
audience north india south india and so
on so the genetic input is very less
especially in india and
it proves there was no invasion first of
all and in turkey again you find the
majority of the genetics are local all
right sir
okay thank you sir thank you
thank you great question thank you bye
okay let us bring in somebody else
i will need to see your faces gentlemen
ladies if i want to bring you in
i will need to see people's faces anyway
let's bring in
mr arush
so
my question was that what are the
problems in today's
present
defense industry of india where new
entrepreneurs can contribute in because
if we go in
making weapons some even some new
weapons it needs a lot of money
so where can some entrepreneurs start
what are the main problems in today's
drdo and other defense industries of
india
uh let me answer the question about
entrepreneurs drdo and defense
industries are a whole different kettle
of fish
so let's say you are a new engineering
graduate you have lots of ideas and you
want to start a
artillery business a company that
manufactures let's say artillery weapons
you know how it serves or whatever
so you want to do that you know that you
know the business i mean you know the
how to do it you've studied engineering
you have the degree and all the question
is even if you're motivated and all that
how will you find the funding you need
funding
to create a business you need funding to
do rnd and create a better weapon which
needs a lot of testing lot of iteration
you create a certain prototype of a
weapon it may not perform to your
expectations then you will try to
improve it by creating a newer version
so all of this takes funding you need
manpower you need to
hire
to hire employees you need a building or
buildings and so on so you need funding
who's gonna provide the funding an idea
is not enough so the question right now
in india is how do people with great
ideas and the
and the capability to execute on those
ideas how do they get funding
so there is this
scheme of the government called startup
india i have not looked into the details
of how it works but i think they are
providing funding to uh promising
startups and all that we also have
venture capital and all but in in terms
of venture capital when you go into that
they will expect a big return on their
investment and within a reasonable time
frame in certain industries like defense
and all the return on investment may
take longer than what these people
expect so these are the problems and
also you have all the bureaucratic red
tape if you want to incorporate a
company you have to go through all these
procedures all the hoops that you have
to jump through
and so on so there are lots of problems
it's not very easy to do business in
india
uh the ease of doing business rankings
are certainly improving over the past
five seven years but i think a lot more
can be done of course india is producing
the most number of startups
in the world right now we have uh
leapfrog china also in that so clearly
the government is doing certain things
right maybe many things right and yet
there is a lot of room for improvement
so i would say the main problem that
people face youngsters face when they
come out of the engineering and whatever
other thing they're coming out and they
have ideas the main problem is how do
you get funding there is no access to
funding you may have an idea but without
funding you can't do it so these are
some of the problems that india is
facing
so that's what i consider say to you
so so
do we need every any extra kind of
experience
for that
for what uh for making some new weapons
like uh previous job industries
if you want to if you want to develop
weapons you need a solid background in
engineering
structural engineering the metallurgy
and lots of other things you will also
need to know ballistics and all kinds of
other things so you need a scientific
engineering background to be able to do
this right
okay thank you sir can't believe that
thank you so much
thank you so much pleasure to have you
bye
all right
okay who has who else has been waiting
let's bring in mr
samarth
hello sir
how are you doing
nice to meet you sir
so here's my question
i've been a nature lover since childhood
and i've noticed that environmentalism
in the modern sense has had a lot of
marxist ideas leftist ideas
why is this so
excellent question excellent question so
what you will see
if you look at the history of
environmental activism which all
originates in the west see the thing is
this environmental uh activism
originates in the west the west has
garnered stolen the entire world's
resources
and per capita their their carbon
emissions their consumption of energy it
is way way ahead of what the rest of the
world uses right the u.s uh
uh consumption of electricity per capita
must be like 25 50 times the rest of the
world per per capita thing so they are
the biggest consumers and destroyers
of the environment and because of this
they really in recent times it has
become fashionable to
indulge in environmental activism in
which they typically blame india and
china so what they do is this
they consume things which are which they
have manufactured in china they don't
want to manufacture it locally because
it costs too much money so they will
outsource all the manufacturing to china
in
some other countries
so these countries like china in the
past few decades have been manufacturing
all the goods for the west now when you
manufacture things
there is
carbon emissions there is an
environmental footprint of what you do
so the west will have china manufacture
this and other countries manufacture
these things and then they will blame
those countries for the carbon emissions
and the pollution and all that that's
what they do that's a hypocrisy
and then what you have seen in recent
times and since the 1960s 70s is that
all these fake ngos not fake but real
ngos have come up which uh
tom tom the entire movement of uh
of environmentalism i can give an
example of greenpeace
so what they do is they try to prevent
progress of the developing countries
they target the developing countries but
they don't really target the worst they
will do some token protests and all that
so all of this has been co-opted
by the uh
by essentially by certain very powerful
forces in the west to keep
eastern countries
uh developing countries to keep
pressurizing them that's what it is and
like you said the marxists the leftists
the so-called liberals fake liberals
they have taken over the movements
feminism has been hijacked
environmental has environmentalism has
been hijacked and all of these are now
using marxist methodologies
to essentially try to keep the east down
because the west
is highly developed the east also wants
to develop why should the the people of
the so-called third world also not have
good living standards but when you try
to bring your living standards up you're
going to have to use environmental
resources and do that and the west
doesn't want that they want us to remain
poor in poverty and always backward so
these are the reasons why they are using
these marxist methodologies in other
frameworks in order to
use environmentalism as a stick to beat
the third world width
so that's what's happening
all right
yeah it's climate politics
climate politics correct
thank you so much for the question nice
to meet you
a big fan thank you so much thank you
bye
okay
all right let's see who else let us
bring in
mr tamil
thank you so much my question was
before the arrival of eastern company
okay so we know that india was one of
the most powerful countries in the world
right
but uh before the arrival of eastern
company how come the britishers
was able to acquire more arms and
ammunitions that they were able to come
in a position to invade india
that is an excellent question so what
you had is that uh
for most of history
uh india was the most i would not say
the most powerful country always but the
most industrially developed country and
the largest economy in the on the whole
planet that is no
known fact india was the first
industrialized civilization going back
5000 years which is also well known i
mean you cannot deny it and the first
urban civilization but india was not
always politically united and when you
are not politically united you are not
powerful because you have lots of
competing
factions or kingdoms within the
subcontinent and they are competing
against each other instead of competing
against the foreigners so what happened
is that india was not united when all
the invasions happened in the past 1000
years
now what happened also
is that the west
uh
when the when the arabs when they when
the turks conquered india parts of north
india
they sent all kinds of
so-called scholars and translators to
india who went to our universities to
our libraries took out all the
interesting texts on metallurgy on
science on astronomy on navigation
on on pharmacology toxicology
mathematics all these things whatever
they find interesting whatever they
found interesting whatever had military
applications actually they took all that
with them they translated it into arabic
and so on persian arabic mostly
and eventually all this was transmitted
to the west so this new source of
knowledge came into the west and the
west was already christianized which is
a political religion it is an imperial
structure so they weaponized all this
knowledge indians had been using this to
develop a peaceful
uh
uh highly evolved society culture
civilization the westerners they used it
in terms of weaponry so they weaponized
this knowledge they found ways of
navigating across the world they found
ways see india was india was the home of
the so called sirik steel the greatest
the most advanced steel making industry
in the world it is now called damascus
steel because it was imported from india
into damascus
so so all of these industries ship
making industry the steel making
industry all of these secrets traveled
to the west they weaponized everything
and then they used it to invade the rest
of the world so the invasions happened
after all of this scientific knowledge
made its way to the west the invasive
mindset was always there but the new
knowledge the new technologies
it these all of this acted as a force
multiplier
and that's how they were able to expand
worldwide and create the these empires
and all do all these genocides so that's
what happened it's a long story and we
it's not always clear because it's not
taught to us so it starts with the
invasions of india but the turks the
the theft of indian knowledge technology
all that first into the islamic world
and from there to europe and the
europeans
were the best at weaponizing this and
that's how they were able to eventually
in the past 500 years developed the
technology to a higher extent and then
conquered the world so that's how it
happened
thank you so much sir it was like nice
meeting you
nice meeting you too very nice meeting
you thank you bye
okay um
whom shall we bring in oh i can see my
dear old friend banu shall we bring in
mr bhano
hello
good evening sir
good evening sir how are you doing
so i'm fine so first of all i want to
apologize sir in your previous uh
uh so i thought you were asking
questions
joined in that day's podcast so i'm
extremely sorry for that
no issues
so sir my question is sir uh can you
tell me about shambhaji maharaj
sir it's very less about him on internet
uh unfortunately i am not an authority
on shambhaji maharaj i have not studied
the maratha history of india to the
extent that i would have liked to study
it but what i can do for you
is please wait for a couple of weeks i'm
going to bring in an expert on maratha
history and i'm going to ask
all the questions
that will give you the answers about all
of this so the first podcast we'll do
discussion conversation we'll do is
going to be about the big picture
perspective of maratha history the
chronology and what happened in the
contributions of the marathas and maybe
i can also bring out the topic of
shambhaji maharaj himself so i
personally as of today have not studied
it sufficiently i am not satisfied that
i know enough
so i am going to ask you to
be a little patient wait for a couple of
weeks and then you will have the answers
on this channel all right sir
thank you very much nice meeting you
again all the best yes
nice bye
okay um
let us bring in mr um
okay very good question so uh
i have before the part before i did the
podcast with mr virendra sinchowhan i as
you know i have expressed my views what
i what views i had about mr prithira
johan that
he was a capable king and all that but
he should not have allowed mr gorey
to escape with his life
he should have the duty of a king is to
protect the country the people and the
long-term national interest and he
failed in doing that now after i had the
conversation detailed conversation with
with mr virendra singh rather
i got to understand that era much better
i got to understand the life and career
of pratyura chauhan much better and what
virendraji brought out is that there was
a battle even before the battles of
taran which was a few years before that
the battle of the satellite
in which president johann had defeated
gory one more time and he had allowed
him to once again uh
kind of spared him
so um
and what mr virender singh
also brought out is that
most of
johan's enemies or adversaries outlived
him despite pethira johan being such a
great warrior and capable warrior so
there clearly seems to be in my opinion
a certain lack of killer instinct he was
too magnanimous
too kind too generous to enemies
right
and
when you talk about greatness how do you
measure the greatness of a king or a
queen or a ruler you measure the
greatness of a king or a queen or ruler
by the
by the um the the the
scale of positive impact they had on
their
on their kingdom and on the people of
the country right and what was their
legacy so if you look at the outcome of
prithviraj chohan's rule he may have
been a great person a very noble minded
person and all that and a brave warrior
but he ended up losing
uh to the turks to to gauri
he presided over the destruction of his
over the end of his dynasty essentially
and the destruction of his kingdom and
the massacres and genocide of his people
the destruction of the temples and
architecture everything so if you look
at the legacy of johan
it is a legacy that is terribly negative
unfortunately as a person he may have
been a very nice person great person but
his legacy is that of defeat
and when a
king's legacy is defeated you cannot
call him a great king unfortunately
so
my view overall has not changed i am
very thankful to viren regi one more
podcast is coming up in the future
very interesting discussion but my
overall big picture view of prathira
chohan has not changed i do not see him
as a king who has a positive legacy i
don't see a king him as a king who
safeguarded the
long-term
national interest of his kingdom and
therefore i do not see him as a great
king unfortunately
sadly
right so i that i hope i answer the
question yes thank you sir thank you
thank you nice to meet you nice to meet
you bye
okay mr i is very impatient let's bring
in mr i
good evening sir
good evening
good evening sir can you hear me
i can hear you but i can't see you
my sister
okay
what's your question
yeah so
sir i currently study in a igcse school
okay
yeah okay so i'm in eighth grade so next
year which is my i have to choose my
subjects
so i just want to ask you
should i choose subjects of my interests
or subjects of less interest but you
know they'll help me economically
in my life in the long term
and i also wanted to know you know so
much about genetics astrophysics and all
that
did you
learn it out of your interests or
did you um
or are you generally educated in this
i know i have learned
and if you did it out of interest then
how did you do it
so all of these subjects that uh
i have learned such as genetics it is it
has never been part of my formal
training formal education my education
formal education is that of a
theoretical physicist not a theoretical
physicist just a physicist but um i
chose theoretical physics but i as you
can i suppose see i have a reasonable
amount of knowledge in other fields as
well like you mentioned genetics so i
studied genetics out of my own interest
the thing i discovered is that if you
have studied
physics to a high level of competence
then it gives you the the tools
that you need to understand other
sciences as well
right physics is the most fundamental
science if you know physics to a high
level of competence you will understand
chemistry very easily it won't take you
much time to to
master chemistry if you if you choose if
you choose to then again biology comes
very easy if you have already studied
physics and
genetics is a sub-branch of biology and
so on and i've always been a very
curious person and so on so forth that's
why i have learned things i have studied
things
out of my own interest over the years so
that's what i've done so that's what i
can answer and as far as your choices
are concerned
you have to
firstly you have to succeed in life in
the long run
like i said
a king's
only duty is to ensure the long-term
prosperity and national interest
security of his kingdom and his people
similarly as a person your duty is to
ensure your personal long-term
prosperity and success so that has to be
paramount
i mean let's say you are into i'm just
giving a hypothetical example let's say
you are passionate about music and you
want to become a guitarist but is there
a long-term career in that you have to
also think of that
so you have to be practical you have to
be pragmatic and life is long you're a
young guy
life is very long you can always follow
your passions later on so i would say
ideally you should find a kind of
synthesis between whatever subjects
interest you and also the subjects that
will give you a long prosperous
financially good career if if the two
don't merge then maybe you should
uh at least temporarily
go for a career that is going to give
you success financial success and the
thing is you should try different things
for the first 10 20 years of your adult
life you can try different professions
based on whatever you studied and
eventually the world will change enough
for you to be able to make a good living
out of whatever
your passions are as well because the
world is changing the world is changing
very fast
so that's what i would say firstly
always ensure that you play defense
properly which means that ensure that
you have a good career right so that
should be the primary motivation a
primary factor that decides your choices
of what kind of subjects you will take
up going forward
alright sir
okay sir thank you
nice meeting you thank you bye
okay let's bring in somebody else i can
see lots of people waiting in the wings
let's bring in mr krishna
hello uh good evening side cell huge
honor for me to be here with you very
nice to meet you good evening
uh so
i just want to ask you that there are so
many speculations regarding uh our rig
veda and
sanskrit as well
so
i just want to know what is the true age
with proper evidence what is the true is
regarding uh the vedas and our sanskrit
and uh what is the proper evidence that
we have regarding uh these two and
occurring archaeological surveillance
recent studies
very good questions are very good uh so
the thing is we don't have hard evidence
that will uh
clearly delineate the exact era in which
the rig veda was written so sanskrit is
a different topic
there's a different topic obviously
the rig veda was written in sanskrit
which means that the sanskrit language
existed before the regulator was written
so let's try and use the rigveda as a
marker for a certain time period so how
do we determine the age of the rig
weather that is a big mystery so if you
look at the uh mainstream historians who
have been writing books for decades they
will say that the aryans invaded india
around 1500 bc in around 1200 bc they
sat on the banks of the saraswati no no
the saraswati is a myth sorry so
around 1200 bc or so they had settled
down enough and destroyed the india and
dravidians enough so that they could
ride the rig veda so that is the
official narrative now if you examine
the text of the rigveda you will find
certain things it's you will find that
it's a snapshot of a certain time period
of indian society our ancestors when
they lived in a certain time period you
will see a snapshot of that time period
and the society and the culture of the
time in this text the rig veda and it
also gives you geographical clues and
things like that for instance it talks
about a lot of rivers
and among these rivers one name is
mentioned more than all other names and
that is the saraswati it talks about the
great river saraswati more than any
other river there are entire sections
devoted to the uh to extolling the
greatness in the virtues of this great
river and the way the river is mentioned
is
in a physical form a great
massive river greater than all of the
rivers a loudly roaring river the mother
of floods so these are physical
depictions not mythological imaginary
depictions so it is clearly mentioning a
river a physical genuine river
now all these decades historians said
there is no such river
where is it it doesn't exist but today
unfortunately geology and science and
satellite images etc they have busted
this myth
if you go and look at the google earth
images etc and you know where to look
you will find an enormous paleo channel
a dry riverbed which runs from the
himalayas down to the so called arabian
sea today all right so you will see that
there was once a massive river a far
greater river than all of the rivers
that actually existed where it is
supposed to have existed and where the
legends said it was so now it is proven
beyond any doubt that the river
saraswati existed
and it is also been determined through
scientific studies geological studies
bioluminescence studies etc that this
river dried out about about 1500 bc
approximately give or take a few
centuries and it was precipitated by a
climate change event mostly so about
6000 bc
what happened is that the indian monsoon
started declining monotonically slowly
slowly gradual decline over centuries
over thousands of years and the decline
eventually went to such an extent that
the river dried out powerfully by 1500
1500 bc
now the rig veda mentions a great
massive river the mother of floods so it
is clear that this text was written
closer to when the river was in its
prime
then to when it dried out and the river
was last in its prime around 6000 bc so
i'm not making the claim
that it was written in 6000 bc but i am
certainly
making the claim it was written closer
to 6000 bc bc than to 1500 bc
so this was a this is this would
indicate that the rig veda is about five
to eight thousand years old most likely
and that would make it the world's
oldest known literature in human
existence
so based on these uh
based on these data points one can reach
an educated guess as to when this text
would have been written but it is still
impossible to pinpoint it accurately but
further research will be done by
scientists not by historians scientists
are going to
lead the research in the 21st century
and hopefully we'll be able to find
better clues and find the actual time
when it was done
so that's what i can offer you sir
sir are there any resources or studies
going on right now regarding the subject
i think right now the main research is
being done by scientists by scientists
from the iits from other institutes
in the in the field of geology in the
field of genetics
linguistics still nothing is happening
but these fields all converge when you
take a scientific approach and they give
clues in multidisciplinary ways so some
research is now happening in india i'm
very glad to say that i have this this
podcast recently with dr nirajaray who
spoke about the genetic history of india
deep genetic history of india and i will
bring in more experts as well so you
will get better information from them as
well right
thank you so much very nice to meet you
sir thank you my pleasure
thank you bye
okay
very interesting questions let us bring
in some other people uh mr anish has
been waiting for a while
hello
namaste namaste i cannot hear you sir
please unmute your mic
now it's coming
yes sir i can hear you now how are you
doing sir nice to meet you
yes sir i'm creating class 12 currently
okay and sir my question is sir
now the budget is going to be announced
budget the uh this this year
sir and the two years of the two years
have been lost due to corona um so what
are your expectations and so where are
you going to see the indus economy long
term means till 2030 till 2035 what are
your views that way
right very good question so like you
rightly point out the last two years
have been wiped out from the indian
economy because of the pandemic the
entire world has seen the same
phenomenon and india's economy for some
time it actually went backwards there
was a contraction in the economy in the
gdp data
now the economy is projected to grow for
the next couple of years nine percent
eight percent something like that
i see i am not an economist there is one
field that i cannot claim any kind of
expertise in so i don't know what sort
of budget we should expect but what i
would like to see from a macro
perspective over the next decade i would
like to say 10 plus growth year upon
year in the indian economy
that is imperative that it is
non-negotiable we need 10 plus growth
every year for the next 20 years
actually and the government needs to
find ways of doing this eight percent
nine nine percent is okay
but we need ten percent plus that is
mandatory if india has to become a great
power and india has to raise the living
standards to the to the to the level
that the people deserve so this needs to
happen over the next 20 years so uh
i'm not sure how
what specific concrete steps the
government should take we should
obviously look at things like making it
easier to do business in india
encouraging startups further creating
more infrastructure investing in
infrastructure roads railways
these things
and uh private opening up the industries
and all that privatizing things which
are currently in the government sector
and all so many things can be done maybe
i should call some economists to explain
this in more detail but what needs to
happen from a macro perspective is
anyhow the government needs to find ways
over the next 20 years to sustain
10 plus growth in the economy that is
what this country needs
do you think that this government is
going in the right direction according
to
i think of all the governments yeah good
question so of all the governments i
have seen in my lifetime this government
gives me the most hope i don't know what
the media says i don't know what other
vloggers say
i do not
base my
uh understanding of things on the
opinions of other people i see the data
and i
base my understanding and opinions based
on the data only and based on all that i
can say this is the government that
gives me the most hope of all the
governments i've seen in my lifetime so
i am positive
right
thank you sir
thank you so much for the question very
nice to meet you
um all right
okay let us bring in mr um
mr skanda prasad
nice to meet you sir
yeah yeah uh so my question is that
there's a speculation that the
government of india
passed in 1935
has been trimmed down and it's been
tweaked to give us the uh constitution
of india
so the thing is then what exactly was
the contribution of dr ambedkar and the
other members of the committee who you
know made the constitution
right good question very good question
so you
could you mute your mic it's it's
echoing
thank you so much thank you thank you
okay so your question is a very good
question and you are right the indian
constitution is essentially based on the
1935 act which was passed by the british
no doubt about it the fundamental
framework is that of the 1935 act
and that was then built upon by the
so-called constituent assembly
and then it was put out as the indian
constitution now
we should see what dr ambedkar himself
had to say about this
right so i am not
an expert in the life and times and work
of dr ambedkar but if i recall correctly
he wanted a different constitution for
india if i recall correctly he wanted a
presidential system for india he wanted
a whole
lot of other things for india which have
not been included in the indian
constitution
he was kind of made to rubber stamp the
constitution that was still very much
colored in nature there is no doubt that
he was a very learned man
and he
he could have drawn a constitution that
would have been far better for all of us
it would have been very useful even
today unfortunately it looks like he was
not allowed to do that
i
would repeat that i am not an expert in
the life and times and work of dr
ambedkar but this is the sense that i
have got thus far maybe i will bring in
somebody who's an actual expert and who
has studied this in far more detail and
then we can bring that out also but yes
i would say that
i would say that he wanted a different
kind of constitution for india
right right thank you hopefully we have
a dharmic constitution somewhere for our
country
one hope so also
thank you see you thank you nice to meet
you bye
um
okay let us bring in some other
people
uh whom do i bring in
let us bring in mr nithyananda
good evening good day
good evening sir
namaste
namaste my question was that our
constitution is pathetic i accept it
but is there a secondary constitution
like we have the arthashastra but
somehow due to modern day technology the
arthashastra certain parts will not be
applicable for now so is there any
constitution which can be implemented in
place of the constitution which is now
there
yeah very good question see the
arthashastra essentially is a set of
principles that can be extrapolated to
any time period in indian history or
world
the shasta history not essentially not
actually a constitution per se it is a
set of principles guidelines it's a rule
book on
how to uh
how to conduct your state craft how to
run
an empire and a big economy
what kind of laws should you have and so
on so forth so it's it's a template for
running
essentially a subcontinent-sized country
or empire or whatever it is
so uh i would not say that the
arthashastra could substitute as a
constitution
what we have to look back upon is how
did
our past rulers
run
the country
especially when the country was unified
under a single empire or ruler we have
the mauryan era we have the era of the
kanishka koshan the great kanishka one
of our greatest emperors
we have the gupta era we have
the
cholas the marathas so how did they run
the country and they ran the country
without a written constitution by the
way
they did not need a written constitution
to run the country
right
and they were able to run the country
brilliantly far better than the way it
is run today and if you look at certain
countries like the uk they don't have a
written constitution they are also able
to manage their affairs very well
so you don't necessarily
need a written constitution
what you need is proper policies
proper governance mechanisms
and the right way of running the country
and a proper set of laws codified set of
laws if you have that you can run the
country brilliantly and what i would say
is that whatever way it is done it
should be done done according to the
precepts of indian culture and
civilization in a dharmic way that's it
that is what will take the country
forward nothing else
so that's what i would say we don't
really even need a written constitution
we can do without that
so certainly
it is said that monarchy is the right
form of government so do you agree with
it
let's look at the last 10 000 years of
human history
and let's look at all the successful
culture civilizations empires what form
of them what form of government did they
have
this democracy that has been imposed
upon the world in the last 100 years or
so
it is an experiment
it is not something that is proven to
work i mean look at the experiments in
democracy in various parts of the world
what do you see happening there
corruption
disasters and
democracy has
was born in india india is the
birthplace of democracy but we already
we always had a hybrid system we had
democracy at the lower levels and an
emperor at the higher level that's how
it was done so people always had
the power to make changes that were
better best for them they had the right
to appoint officials locally and all
that but at the top it was the there was
the overall supervisory
role of the emperor so it was always
always a hybrid system so the
arthashastra simply reflects that
and i i see nothing contradictory to
that in if you look at the record of
human history the most successful
form of government historically in the
past 10 000 years has never been the
pure democracy the so-called pure
democracy we see today it's always been
a monarchy system so
so the history bears that out
unfortunately or fortunately whichever
way you see it right
thank you sir we love to meet you nice
to meet you thank you for the questions
thank you bye
all right um
whom do we call in let me bring in
let's bring in mr kabir
oops he's gone
sorry it looks like he went off so let's
bring in somebody else
let's bring in mr
yash let's bring in mr josh
hello
namaste
nice to meet you thank you sir
so my question is the artificial robot
mentioned in rather bold time it is to
sir
i'm sorry i didn't get you please repeat
that
artificial robot
in the raja boston
i listen that
it is true or
okay the question is was there an
artificial robot in raja bhoja's time
uh well i i have not come across this
piece of information so i
don't know about it unfortunately
i have never i have never come across
this this
this claim or this record of any robot
existing at that time so unfortunately
i don't know i don't know sorry
do you know please make the video fun
i will look into it certainly all right
thank you so much nice to meet you
thank you sir bye
thank you thank you bye
okay let us bring in um
let us bring in mr prakhar
hello
can't hear you you muted could you
please unmute the mic
yes you are
yeah so first of all truly grateful for
the opportunity
uh
and i wanted to ask like uh
we know that uh mobas did horrific
things like uh genocides and was stopped
to think
but uh
still like uh
they conquered uh the kingdoms according
to like
the correct way like uh for example
british has divided
and ruled
uh like uh they were not moderately
correct uh you know like more like
morality is obviously subjective
but still
uh whatever you know
in front of the principles like uh
dharmic principle
they were correct in some way like uh
they defeated the uh previous king and
took over the nature
kingdom so what are the like things that
are
not uh yet known in the common uh men's
mainstream that uh mughals committed
they were like
really
uh wrong for that sort of principle like
morally wrong principally though
okay okay very good question i get it so
you're talking about the ethics and
morality of warfare what is right in
warfare what is wrong in warfare what
did the mughals do right what did the
british do wrong that sort of thing
see
in the 21st century or even the
we are currently in the so-called
kalyuga age right
so in the kali yuga age kali yuga
the only morality of warfare is that you
must win and the enemy must lose
that is the only morality the only
objective of warfare you go to war when
you fail to achieve your political
objectives through diplomatic means
when you fail to object uh to achieve
your political objectives through
diplomatic means then if you are strong
enough if you have the ability the
capability then you go to war then you
try to achieve your objectives through
military means then the objective of
warfare is very simple
the objective is to win it doesn't
matter how you win it there is no
cheating there is no no nothing no such
thing in warfare and that is
unfortunately something that our rulers
at some point in time failed to grasp
they tried to
wage war in a in a moral ethical way and
that's why they lost the the turks had
no such compulsions or qualms they were
happy to
break the rules that the indians would
not break and that's why the indians
lost now
the british had their own way of
fighting war they they also indulged in
politics in the divide and rule divide
and conquer kind of policy so all of
this is all valid in warfare the thing
that is unethical is the way you treat
the conquered people
that is the most horrific thing these
people have done and there is no real
difference between what the turks did
and what the british did even our kings
and emperors used to wage war they used
to fight among these amongst each other
it is known if you look at the expansion
of the gupta empire it is it was done by
conquering all the kingdoms in india all
the way down south by by let's say
samudragupta
what samudragupta would do is after he
would defeat a certain king he would
reinstate the king
and keep him as a governor who would
send tribute to some of the gupta and
the civilian population was never ever
harmed no civilian was killed no
civilian was abused or hurt nothing was
destroyed there was no burning no
looting no pillaging nothing
and these are the ethics that indians
always had the turks and the europeans
they broke all these ethics and that's
just the way the world is today it is a
terrible world you can see all the same
things happening in the 21st century as
well
so to summarize i would say
that from a realistic perspective from
the chanakyan perspective
you have to expect your enemy to be the
worst form of barbarian you cannot
expect the enemy to follow any rules you
have to be prepared for all
eventualities
right so the only objective of warfare
is to win and these guys knew that we
unfortunately at that time we did not
know that the marathas knew it the
marathas knew how to win they were happy
to cheat and deceive the the the turks
and they were able to win so the
marathas had a very different philosophy
of warfare so it's very interesting all
these things that you brought out but
overall
the only purpose of warfare is victory
achieve it anyhow that's the way the
world works whether we like it or not
okay uh thank you thank you for giving
thank you for a great question nice to
meet you
all right let's bring in
let's bring in mr nitin raddi
nice to meet you
so my question is why netaji called
gandhi as father of nation
okay good question so why did nitaji
make a certain statement you know the
world doesn't work on the basis of talk
in statements
you make certain statements
for political purposes there is a
tactical reason for making the statement
a or statement b
when i say if how do you um
how do you
analyze or how do you study the the
career of a leader
what you do is you have to ignore their
statements and look at their actions
look at their actions
where netaji's actions in in line with
gandhiji's philosophy mr mohandas gandhi
said don't fight
be non-violent be passive be reactive
let the british do whatever they want
but then let the
other forces do whatever they want but
never fight back only protest
non-violently through satyagraha now let
us look at his career and his actions
his career and his actions and his
philosophy were the exact opposite of
that
so he may have made a tactical statement
while he was still a member of the
congress party to appease mr gandhi
because mr gandhi was very powerful
politically in the congress party so
from a political perspective he may have
made a statement here and there
ignore the statements indians are
they have this great fetishization of
words indians look at statements words
words are so important no words are not
important only actions matter
only actions matter and if you look at
the actions of netanyahu they are
completely
against the philosophy
and and the teachings of mr gandhi so i
think that should tell you everything
you need to know about nita just
watching the reports
right sir
sir one more thing is how can i meet you
okay how can you meet me physically well
someday we will meet if the gods
make it possible right right now because
of the restrictions and travel and all
that it is not feasible but we can meet
face to face like this right okay sir
all right so thank you very nice to meet
you and thank for thanks for the
question thank you
all right let's bring in some more
people i'll try and bring it bring in
two three more people today
uh who do we have
uh let's bring in mr
mr aishwarya shukla
hello
hello sir how are you
i'm very well how are you doing i'm just
fine uh actually i'll just
jump into the question first
uh because of marvel nowadays everyone
is you know have something
have some knowledge about the multiverse
and i've read some things that that
contains a word like hindu multiverse
like there are 14 lokas in something
and
that make up hindu do you have any
knowledge regarding hindu multiverse
uh i am primarily a scientist and then i
am a historian so i am not an expert in
deep uh
in in topics like what are the the
different locus and all that i am not an
expert in this so i think i would not be
the right person to ask this question
you want to talk about the theory the
multiverse from the physics perspective
i can give you a two hour lecture on
that of course it is not a physics
perspective it's a philosophical
perspective when you talk about the
hindu multiverse it's a spiritual thing
philosophical and spiritual thing so it
is something that is not a scientific
theory it's a philosophical theory and a
spiritual uh
world view right
it's actually sorry to interrupt you
it's actually mentioned in the hindu
mythology now that's why i that's why i
thought that i can yes i'm aware of that
i'm aware that it's it's mentioned there
are all these different locus that are
mentioned
and there are many other higher realms
of existence and all that but i am not a
student of that i have not been a
student of that i would love to study
that if i find the time in this life but
unfortunately i have certain pursuits
that i am focusing more on right now so
i am not the expert in this and if i
would give you an answer from my
personal perspective it may actually be
incorrect in some ways possibly i i
don't know so that's why i would not
venture to give a comment about that you
know so i hope you understand me yeah
big fan for it thank you thank you so
much very nice to meet you very nice to
meet you thank you
bye-bye
okay um
let us bring in mr
raghav hello good evening
hi
uh i uh i'm in gurgaon my name is robert
trapati and i have a burning question
regarding the history of the harappans
and
mohenjo-daros so uh the people of uh
uh
after this uh service they planned uh
great cities build great cities but
after the river sarswati dried out they
moved towards
the ganges
ganges
river
and
for example kashi they did not care to
build um
such great planned cities uh for example
my dad uh he was uh he is from
nade
uh venaris
and he
told me this question and i thought it
would be great to ask
it
very good question it's an interesting
question so if you see uh
if you look at the time period of the
the so-called harappan era the harappan
phase of india civilization you find
that you had this massive urbanized
civilization in the western region of
india the so-called region of the seven
river satya sindhu region where you have
the great cities of bharapa mahindra
kalibangan
and so many more and even the small
towns were very well planned and their
multi-storied buildings it was a clear
sign of a very advanced technologically
advanced urban civilization
and like you rightly mentioned then
there was climate change the great river
dried out and then there was a gradual
migration of the people from this region
eastwards into the ganga plain the
yamuna plain and
in the other river valleys of
within the indian subcontinent india is
essentially a river valley civilization
it's always been settled around in river
valleys so there are many major rivers
in other parts of india eastwood so
that's where they went now if you look
at the archaeological record from the
time you find that
at the same time you had other people
who lived in eastern parts of india
contemporaneous to the harappan people
but they in that region the
uh
the urbanization was not is not visible
to that extent so you don't find
multi-storied buildings from 5000 years
ago in the ganga valley the yamuna
valley for instance that that's what we
find
maybe uh maybe there was erosion maybe
the archaeological research has not been
done properly but we don't find it thus
far
so what happened is that the migration
happened from westwards western india
into central india eastern india and
these populations they assimilated the
mixed intermixed end elements of
whatever practices the westerners had
mingled with the practices of the
easterners and later on you had great
cities that came up even in other parts
of india later on so there was a phase
in which there was this period of
migration period of flux and period of
less development and then again you find
development of big empires big cities
all across india look at the ancient
city of partly putra which is about five
to two thousand five hundred years old a
great metropolitan city and even if you
look at the city of kashi varanasi
banaras you find that the oldest
archaeological evidence that you find in
the city is about eight nine thousand
years old and nobody has done any proper
archaeological excavation there i dare
say that if archaeologists were to do
their work and excavate the the
the relevant parts of the city they may
find
urban structures big structures even
there you know deep deep hidden in the
soil so the thing is we have
excavated or studied less than two
percent of the indian subcontinent from
an archaeological perspective and that's
why there are so many gaps in our
understanding
of our ancient history but that's what i
can offer you in brief it's a very
interesting question that you've asked
me and i would encourage you to study
further very interesting uh history that
we have right
yeah thank you uh yeah uh thank you for
answering that question uh huge fan of
yours uh we listen to your
broadcasts every day and yeah i better
be heading out now
thank you so much very nice to meet you
and all the best thank you bye thank you
bye
okay let me i think we have time for
let me take two more people in one
two more
guests
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
let's bring in mr neil
hello
good evening sir
good evening how are you doing
i'm fine sir sir i wanted to ask um
this is my opinion but
uh
doesn't reading too much books about
different personalities destroy our own
critical thinking ability so for example
thousand year before today there were
not many books but still there were many
great thinkers like
might not have read many books to
uh write earth
so sir what's your opinion about this
okay very good question so if you read
too much you may get too much
too much too much data in your head and
you will not be able to develop your own
personality that is the perspective you
are offering here
so i and what you're saying is that we
did not have a lot of books in the past
and we have too many today so i would
offer you
a different perspective
a thousand years before today we had
a large number of great universities
across the country and each of these
universities had
a huge library you had libraries all
across the country and all of these
universities were raised to the ground
by the turks and all the libraries were
burned it is well known it is recorded
by observers that the great library in
nalanda burned for months
it burned for months so imagine the
number of books we had there and in a
university library you have books on all
topics your books on the sciences on
astronomy on mathematics and philosophy
on culture and spirituality on history
historical records for thousands of that
went back thousands of years back into
india's past and that is just one
library we had so many universities
and so on so forth
so i think india was the land of
learning you had millions of books all
across the length and the breadth of the
country
all right
so historically we have had books and
people were reading books i would say
that if you
ingest let's say you are consuming data
by reading books and you read let's say
a hundred books in in two years or three
years
it's going to give you different
perspectives it's going to broaden your
horizons and give you different kinds of
data and different kinds of knowledge
now it's up to you what you do with the
knowledge you can
choose to believe some of the knowledge
you must choose to reject some of the
knowledge you may allow some of this
knowledge to shape a certain kind of
world view
and it is all it all depends on you so
you are the final arbiter of what you do
with the knowledge that you may choose
to in to to consume
so i would say from my perspective this
is my personal perspective you don't
have to agree with it it's perfectly
fine my perspective is that if you read
more if you gain more knowledge either
by reading books or watching
documentaries or listening to podcasts
or whichever
way works for you if you expose yourself
to more information to more perspectives
it kind of broadens your horizons and
gives you a better perspective of the
world and then you can draw your own
conclusions it will not destroy your
personality i don't think so
uh sir of course factual documentaries
that we have to listen but i am talking
about self-help books like how to cure
depression what this that kind of thing
you know so okay i was not aware that
you're talking about fake books
answer reading autobiographies of people
how they overcame obstacles in their
life i'm talking about that sense but i
totally understand what you are saying
right right so that's what i can say
it's all about perspectives of course
these days you have all kinds of
opinions that are being
uh marketed as knowledge so that is
always a problem self-help is has become
a big industry for some reason
uh so it's up to you whether you want to
consume that i think eventually you will
if you read enough self-help books you
will start understanding that all of
this is also marketing and much of it is
actually incorrect so
you have to trust your own wisdom and
and judgment that's what that's what i
would say
yes thank you sir nice to meet you thank
you very much bye
okay let's bring in um
let's bring in
charmi good evening good day good
evening
how are you sir
i'm good how are you doing
uh so my i'll just straight away come to
the question
so sir like we know now that uh the iron
invasion theory is is false and uh
and by by various sources it's been
proven that
it's rather india out of india theories
is a lot more valid
uh but when you talk to the south indian
people they are very good friend of mine
and very very good people
but they still tell that like no that
the aryan invasion theory proving wrong
is actually propaganda
and so how do you deal with that kind of
mindset and there are lots of prominent
uh
people who still are not accepting this
and like i mean they i mean uh
how would i say uh the breaking india
force is still kind of like you know
uh trying to prove uh it's it's a wrong
theory so
yes how do we deal with it
right so the point you have raised is is
absolutely correct very valid and i
would say that this attitude is mostly
prevalent in tamil nadu and kerala more
than other southern states if you look
at karnataka
you don't see this attitude at all so
it's only in a couple of regions which
you which you like you said and what you
find is that
see i don't blame these people for the
beliefs they hold these are all nice
people i know so many of them and the
thing is that today what we have is that
the education system has not doesn't
give us the ability to
to dis of discernment what is right what
is wrong how do you reach the right
conclusions it doesn't teach you
how to do this the education system
simply tells you that trust that obey
authority and believe whatever your
teacher says so today that has been
replaced by all these authors and all
these propagandists
who go on the media if you look at the
tamil media if you look at the tamil
political ecosystem they are all very
much anti north india and they are very
much tamil supremacist
and they it is it is
in their benefit
it helps the politicians if they keep
this aryan invasion theory alive because
it creates a a sense of victimhood that
we have been oppressed and then that
politicians can claim that we
politicians are going to help you and
we're going to save you from this
oppression we're going to uplift you
yeah so politics it's all based on
creating divisions fractions and all
those things so that's why the
politicians
have kept this theory alive the
politicians have all the money and
that's why the media also does that
because they are bought by the
politicians and the academics and all
that and of course like you mentioned
there are these breaking india forces
who want to keep these theories alive to
create these divisions within the rest
of indian society they will say that the
tribals are the real uh
dravidians of india and the fair-skinned
people are the audience and all the
nonsense so it is all a battle of
perception the
the factual data has nothing to do with
all these theories that are being put
out and the narratives that are being
peddled
so what needs to do is if you want to
combat this we have to reform the
education system and give the young kids
the ability
of of discernment how to judge what is
right and what is wrong how to recognize
false
news fake news from real news and all
those things you know so that is
unfortunately it's going to be a long
long haul because we have not even taken
the first steps towards that in the
meanwhile what we can do is we can keep
disseminating what the real facts are
based on scientific evidence that's all
we can do but thank you for the question
very good question
thank you sir and answer one request uh
you should try to do some live streams
sometimes uh a different time because in
australia it's already like you know
too late or rather too early morning so
it's it's nice
uh australia
you're in australia okay so
i will i will see how that works my my
main audience is in india unfortunately
so you know
it's always going to be inconvenient for
some people here and there but hopefully
you can watch a replay of the live
stream
sometimes sometimes i'm just saying not
all the time but sometimes all right
all right keep in mind
thank you nice to meet you bye
okay let's bring in one final person for
today and who's gonna be the lucky lucky
person let me see
let's bring in kaya
hello good
[Music]
i have a lot of evening to make
so it's basically i'm just going to talk
about the status of women and all of
that
things related to that and so firstly i
think i'd like to start by uh
by like starting i'm going to start with
sex education
so sex education
is it's not imparted to kids and uh the
thing is that uh
you know i've been kind of reading all
of this stuff and the thing that the
constitution is egalitarian the
constitution does not discriminate and
the constitution is actually it's more
liberal towards women as compared to men
but you know the source of all of this
uh i would say discrimination i think it
kind of has something to do with the
sexual progressiveness of the society
and you know no one no one talks about
these things and no one wants to talk
about these things because you know
they're considered taboos in long time
and there's so much there's so much
blatant sexualization that kind of
disgusts me
i used to watch this yo-yo honey singing
person
and um in one of his videos you know
he's just sitting on his chair he he's
fully clothed and he's wearing all these
clothes and you know they're just
there's just women around him wearing
scanty clothes and
i mean all of that
and and interestingly interestingly in
india india was i
have studied about it india was pretty
progressive you know karma sutra and uh
we have obviously the temples of kajar
and all of that and the thing is that
this modesty
kind of comes from monotheistic
religions christianity there's a you
know great emphasis on virginity and all
of that and
covering up is i think it's
you know greatly islam and all of that
so how do we change this perspective of
the society
and and women get a lot of free threats
women get a lot of rape threats you know
whenever they mention their points or
something like that there's always so
much citation of sexual violence i don't
think so much of discrimination
happening on um
i would say okay that that's it
okay okay you bring up uh an interesting
perspective so what you are saying is
right india's indian society has
regressed a lot
and i would say that if you want to
understand the source of this regression
you have to look at the history of the
past thousand years when
foreign cultures were imposed upon india
when those
narratives those world views became the
dominating and ruling world views in
india and the constitution like you said
has a certain slant and all that but if
you look at the history of india like
you mentioned it has been a very
different kind of history if you look at
the indigenous original culture of india
if you look at the carvings that we find
in history men women you can see there
was no emphasis on covering up there was
no need to be to feel ashamed for or
showing uh various body parts or
whatever if you look at the temples in
kajura if you look at the various
carvings of gods goddesses ordinary
people in caves and temples across india
you find that india has always been a
very egalitarian liberal society there
was no
sense of fake modesty of covering up and
all that a very open society
and women had no need to cover up there
was no
sense of fear if you do that and all
that and and i would say that the best
representation of what indian society
would have been like a thousand years
ago
is what you can see in southeast asia in
places like thailand in in places like
cambodia which still
retain a significant amount of elements
of indian culture and you can see there
that there is no emphasis on covering up
and fake modesty and all that right
so that's what you see now what's
happened is the past 1000 years of
destruction of indian society of the
foundation of the frameworks of indian
society and that's why we are left with
where we are today now what needs to
happen is we need to remove all the
foreign elements from our society
especially the negative ones but not
overnight it's not going to happen
overnight it's going to happen if india
is allowed to uh
to evolve again properly it's going to
happen over the next 100 or 200 years
it's a long term project it's not going
to happen overnight but what we can
start with is by
changing
the constitution and the laws and and
making it more
i would say right now the constitution
claims to be liberal and egalitarian and
progressive but there are lots of
problems in the constitution and the
laws also and the attitudes of the
judiciary and all towards things in the
government governance mechanism overall
so this is something that has happened
in india over a period of 1000 years
so to undo this will also take some time
so that's what i can say but i agree
with you
can i please just add an ad like one
more question so uh only one question
per person unfortunately only one i have
to treat everybody equally so
all right thank you very much for the
question thank you nice meeting you bye
okay i think i've
should i take one last person
let's take one last person let's bring
in mr udit
hello
hello so can you hear me sir
i can hear you yes
sir i have a question related to russia
sir in in the current news we received
the news that russia's in geopolitical
question from geopolitics sir
we received the news that uh the
population has dropped by
about a million and the population which
is left
only 40 percent is in the working force
like who are able to work or something
sir
in that they're saying that now that
russia is planning to invade ukraine
take parts and bring ussr braxtor
does that have any relation with the
population drop sir
uh i think the geopolitical policies and
ambitions of the russian
ruling class essentially mr putin have
nothing to do with the population drop
or anything the population drop and the
and the aging of the population or the
whatever you're seeing over there that
is a long-term phenomenon it happens on
on a decade by decade level
the geopolitical situation that you are
witnessing in ukraine in europe all that
has to do with the posturing of nato uh
it has to do with the uh emerging uh
cooperation between russia and china
it has something to do with the fact
that there is this uh winter olympics
that's going to happen very soon in
china so
the chinese and the russians are
cooperating to some extent so the
geopolitical considerations have nothing
to do with the population demographics
and whatever is happening on that front
geopolitical considerations are
short-term i mean you can see the
effects right now the population shifts
will be seen over a matter of decades
so that can be something in the
background but the what's happening in
ukraine right now would not have
anything to do with the population shift
in russia
okay so thank you so that that's all
that's right thank you so much thanks
for giving me a chance nice to meet you
thank you thank you thank you thank you
bye
all right my friends i think uh we are
at the end of today's session my
apologies to those of you who are still
waiting uh maybe next time
so this brings us to the end of today's
session very interesting session very
interesting to very nice to interact
with you all and meet you all
and we'll keep doing this once or twice
a month these face-to-face sessions so
thank you so much wonderful taking the
questions and i will see you in the next
episode thank you
bye